{"tossups": [{"question": "In a painting by this man inspired by Livy, three brothers salute swords held by their father while swearing to fight three brothers from Alba Longa. In a painting by this man, a French Revolutionary who was fatally stabbed by Charlotte Corday lies holding a pen in his bathtub. For 10 points, name this French Neoclassical artist of <em>The Oath of the Horatii</em> and <em>TheDeath of</em> <em>Marat</em>.", "answer": "Jacques-Louis <b><u>David</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "An epic poem in this language describes a city named Tambuka. The Kilwa sultanate ruled a coast that shares its name with this language, which Julius Nyerere championed. Due to contact with Arab slave traders in places like Zanzibar, speakers of this language derived many loanwords from Arabic. For 10 points, name this Bantu language, a <em>lingua franca</em> of east Africa.", "answer": "<b><u>Swahili</u></b> language [or <b><u>Kiswahili</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man started his career in organized crime as an associate of Tony Accardo, who controlled several corrupt sherrifs in Texas. This man made a strange remark to Seth Kantor at Parkland Hospital; later, he went to the Dallas police headquarters and claimed he was trying to \"spare Jackie from testifying.\" For 10 points, name this man who killed Lee Harvey Oswald.", "answer": "Jack <b><u>Ruby</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During these people\u2019s siege of Hippo, St. Augustine died. The father of the Roman general Stilicho was one of these people, who were divided into two main groups called the Silingi and the Hasdingi. The vacant crown of the Alans was given to their king Gunderic, while in 455, their king Genseric looted Rome. For 10 points, name this tribe whose name is now a byword for senseless destruction.", "answer": "<b><u>Vandal</u></b>s [or <b><u>Vandali</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "One painting of this event incorrectly includes Maria Letizia Ramolino. It was officiated by Pope Pius VII and held at Notre Dame de Paris, a conscious break from the traditional location of Reims. During this event, its subject surprisingly grabbed the crown and placed it on his own head. For 10 points, name this 1804 crowning of the first Emperor of the French.", "answer": "Coronation of <b><u>Napoleon</u></b> Bonaparte [or <b><u>Coronation of Napoleon I</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "As a player, coach, and manager, this man has participated in more World Series than any other man at 21. A famous photo shows him jumping into Don Larsen's arms after having caught Larsen's perfect game for the Yankees during the 1956 World Series. Nowadays, this man is well known for his humorous quotes such as \u201cif you see a fork in the road, take it\u201d. For 10 points, name this longtime New York Yankee catcher whose name was the inspiration for a famous cartoon character.", "answer": "Yogi <b><u>Berra</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This man orchestrated the starvation of millions of people in the Holodomor famine. The 1956 \u201cSecret Speech\u201d attacked this man for creating a personality cult. His foreign minister signed a non-aggression pact with Joachim von Ribbentrop, but joined the Allies after Germany invaded his country in 1941. For 10 points, name this Soviet dictator who succeeded Vladimir Lenin.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>Stalin</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The discoverer of this body wanted to call it Georgium Sidus, but was overruled by colleagues. The discoverer of this planet also first observed its moons Titania and Oberon. Another planet was discovered when John Couch Adams noticed irregularities in this planet's motion. For 10 points, name this planet discovered by William Herschel, the first new planet since antiquity.", "answer": "<b><u>Uranus</u></b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "A founder of this philosophy posited that the ultimate horror is \"being trampled to death by geese\" and used the metaphor of crop rotation to explain how aesthetes live. This philosophy, which was equated with \"a humanism\" by a French proponent, was originated by Soren Kierkegaard. For 10 points, name this philosophy of Albert Camus and Jean-Paul Sartre.", "answer": "<b><u>existentialism</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This project was supervised by \"Chief\" Thomas MacDonald, who implemented general directives such as the Phipps Act and Pershing Map. This project carved out an exception to its usual rules in Breezewood, Pennsylvania, and it was championed by Dwight Eisenhower, who admired the German autobahn. For 10 points, name this national road network.", "answer": "<b><u>Interstate Highway</u></b> System (prompt on \u201cNational Highway\u201d or \u201cHighway\u201d)  <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 7 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 2014, a letter from this person to George Putnam was discovered showing her interest in a nonconventional marriage. This member of the Ninety-Nines achieved fame after landing in Northern Ireland, and later departed with Fred Noonan on a trip that was last tracked at Howland Island. For 10 points, name this aviatrix who disappeared in 1937 over the Pacific.", "answer": "Amelia <b><u>Earhart</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This territory controls the small Snake Island as well as the island of Vieques (<b>vee-EY-case</b>), which was the site of frequent protests prior to closing a naval training range in 2001. Activists from this territory attempted to assassinate Harry Truman in 1950. For 10 points, name this largest U.S. non-state commonwealth, found in the Caribbean.", "answer": "<b><u>Puerto Rico</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "This composer was commissioned by the Russian ambassador to Austria to write the Rasumovsky (<b>RAH-zuh-MAHV-skee</b>) string quartets. Rudolph of Austria was the dedicatee of his <em>Archduke Trio</em> and <em>Emperor Concerto</em>. For 10 points, name this man who was inspired by Napoleon to write the <em>Eroica Symphony</em> and also composed \"F\u00fcr Elise\".", "answer": "Ludwig van <b><u>Beethoven</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Vedic and Indo-Iranian texts use the word <em>ratha</em> for these inanimate objects, implying that Proto-Indo-European speakers had them earlier. Xenophon saw the Persians attach scythes to the sides of these objects. Hattusili and Rameses II used over five thousand of these objects at the 1274 BC battle of Kadesh. For 10 points, name these wheeled military craft pulled by horses.", "answer": "<b><u>chariot</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This event was ended when Attorney General Richard Olney noticed that it was interfering with delivery of the U.S. Mail, giving him broad powers to restrict it. A refusal to intervene in this event made John Peter Altgeld, the governor of Illinois, a hero to the labor movement. For 10 points, name this 1894 Eugene V. Debs-organized strike against a rail car manufacturer.", "answer": "<b><u>Pullman</u></b> Strike", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This country was where the Ogham script was invented and the Brehon laws were used. Thomas Cahill wrote a book about how this country\u2019s people \u201csaved civilization.\u201d The Book of Kells was created in this country. According to legend, a saint drove the snakes off this island. For 10 points, name this island evangelized by St. Patrick.", "answer": "<b><u>Ireland</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A character in the story of this holiday is described with the mysterious epithet \"the Agagite.\" This holiday's story describes the court of a king often thought to be Xerxes (<b>ZERK-seez</b>), who gets rid of his wife Vashti and marries Esther. For 10 points, identify this Jewish holiday which celebrates deliverance from the Persian vizier Haman in a carnival-like atmosphere.", "answer": "<b><u>Purim</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "This man briefly served as governor of California during the Civil War, in a term whose most distinguishing event was his rowing a boat down flooded streets in order to attend his inauguration. He paid Edward Muybridge to take important photographs of running horses. For 10 points, name this Central Pacific Railroad head and namesake of a Palo Alto university.", "answer": "Leland <b><u>Stanford</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This leader oversaw the annexation of Sikkim by referendum. This leader\u2019s son oversaw</u></b> <b><u>a mass sterilization campaign during the (+)</u> Emergency. While going to an interview with Peter Ustinov, this leader was shot by her own (*)</b> bodyguards in retaliation for ordering an attack in Amritsar. For 10 points, name this prime minister of India, the daughter of Jawaharlal Nehru.", "answer": "<b><u>I</u></b>ndira <b><u>Gandhi</u></b> [prompt on <b><u>Gandhi</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A novelist from this country wrote the script for the original car-chase movie</u> </b><em><b><u>Vanishing</u></b></em> <em><b><u>Point</u> </b></em><b><u>and the experimental book</u> </b><em><b><u>Three Trapped Tigers</u></b></em><b><u>. The national poet of this country</u></b> <b><u>wrote the (+)</u> </b><em><b>Versos Sencillos </b></em><b>(VAIR-sos sen-SEE-yos), which contains a version of (*) </b>\"Guantanamera\" (GWAN-tah-nah-MAY-ruh). For 10 points, name this country where Jose Mart\u00ed once wrote against Spain and poets such as Reinaldo Arenas have been suppressed by the Castro regime.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Cuba</u></b> [or Republica de <b><u>Cuba</u></b>]", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "<b><u>This band instigated the so-called \"Riverport Riot\" when its lead singer jumped into the</u></b> <b><u>crowd to fight with a man taking pictures, then quit the show, causing a serious incident</u></b> <b><u>near St. Louis. In 2008, (+)</u> Dr Pepper attempted to make good on a promise to give every American a free can of soda upon the release of this band's tremendously delayed album (*)</b><em>Chinese Democracy</em>. For 10 points, name this 1980s rock band of <em>Use Your Illusion</em> and the song \"November Rain.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Guns n Roses</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1994, this tribe launched an economic program based on the crossbreeding of the</u></b> <b><u>Akhal-Teke and the Appaloosa into their namesake breed of fast horse. This tribe lost the</u></b> <b><u>Battle of Bear Paw during an 1877 (+)</u> war named for them in which they were originally led by Looking Glass. Nelson Miles stopped this tribe's flight to Canada, which was organized by the man who said \"I will (*)</b> fight no more forever.\" For 10 points, name this American Indian tribe of Chief Joseph.", "answer": "<b><u>Nez Perce</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country suffered through a succession crisis when Sebastian I disappeared at the</u></b> <b><u>Battle of the Three Kings. For much of its history, this country was led by rulers from the</u></b> <b><u>House of (+)</u> Aviz. Under leaders like Prince Henry the Navigator, this country patronized expeditions that discovered the Madeira Islands, found (*)</b> Brazil, and circumnavigated the earth for the first time. For 10 points, name this Iberian home of Pedro Cabral and Ferdinand Magellan.", "answer": "<b><u>Portugal</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This woman had to sell her husband's papers and the Montpelier plantation to secure an</u></b> <b><u>income late in life. This woman, who was raised as a Quaker, sold a slave to Daniel</u></b> <b><u>Webster. She performed ceremonial functions for (+)</u> Thomas Jefferson, a widower, while her own husband was (*)</b> Secretary of State. For 10 points, name this First Lady from 1809 to 1817, who is most known for saving the Lansdowne portrait of George Washington from the burning White House.", "answer": "Dolley <b><u>Madison</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this country, forty-one inmates at the David Viloria prison died in November 2014;</u></b> <b><u>the government says the inmates overdosed on medications after breaking into an</u></b> <b><u>infirmary, but human rights monitors blame intentional poisoning. This country also</u></b> <b><u>announced (+)</u> wage cuts following a drop in the price of (*)</b> oil, which comprises nearly all of its exports. For 10 points, name this South American country led by Nicholas Maduro, who succeeded Hugo Chavez.", "answer": "<b><u>Venezuela</u></b> [Bolivarian Republic of <b><u>Venezuela</u></b>; or Republica Bolivariana de <b><u>Venezuela</u></b>]", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This procedure was first worked out using methane collected from the Baltimore sewers</u></b> <b><u>as a sample. James Arnold acquired samples from the tomb of Zoser to further refine this</u></b> <b><u>procedure, for which (+)</u> Willard Libby won a Nobel Prize. This procedure relies on the fact that isotope (*) </b>14 of its namesake element decays at a known rate over time. For 10 points, identify this procedure which determines the age of organic matter chemically.", "answer": "radio<b><u>carbon dating</u></b> <b>NHBB B 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 7 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras \u2013 ONLY READ IF YOU NEED A BACKUP OR TIEBREAKER! </b> <b><u>A legend claims that this man ordered his soldiers to carry dirt in their helmets to build a</u></b> <b><u>hill at Udine so he could see the burning of Aquileia. In 452, he met an embassy led by Pope</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Leo I. An alliance whose leaders included Flavius Aetius and Theodoric I defeated this man\u2019s forces at the Battle of the (*)</b> Catalaunian Plains, turning back his fifth-century invasion of Europe. For 10 points, name this \u201cScourge of God\u201d, a ruler of the Huns.  ANSWER: <b><u>Attila</u></b> the Hun", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}